Finding Aid for Traverse City Refrigerator Company records, 1909-1919
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Traverse City Refrigerator Company records 1909-1919 1909-1915
Traverse City Refrigerator Company.
3 linear feet
9825 Bb 2
Traverse City, Michigan manufacturer of the fireless "wonder cooker and baker" and a line of iceboxes, 1909-1919; records, including general office files, advertising,. minutes and reports, document the firms business activities.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was transferred from the Burton Historical Collection (donor no. 1531 ) in February 1998.
The collection is open for research.
The Traverse City Refrigerator Company was incorporated in August 1909 with capital stock sold at $100,000; that year, 700 shares sold at $100 each. By 1918, the company declared itself "hopelessly insolvent" and ceased business. On June 25, 1919, the stockholders formally dissolved the Traverse City Refrigerator Company and placed it in voluntary trusteeship in order to sell its assets to pay creditors.
For a decade, the Traverse City Refrigerator Company manufactured the fireless "Wonder Cooker and Baker" and a line of wood-encased, non-electric household and specialty refrigerators (i.e. iceboxes). These appliances were manufactured under the patents of their inventor, Forrest V. Detwiler of Chicago. Detwiler also served as the company's principle salesman and product demonstrator.
According to the firm's prospectus, the "Detwiler System" was an innovation employing "a cold water radiator (or 'circulator') in the lining of the refrigerator." The cooling medium was the water dripping from melting ice then passed through the circulator, which, according to the Traverse City Refrigerator Company, delivered "an absolutely dry cold to the food chamber."
The enterprise was largely the creation of R. Floyd Clinch, who served as the company's vice-president and was a pioneer in the initial development of the Traverse City area. Clinch was the son-in-law of A. Tracey Lay, co-founder of the Hannah and Lay Lumber Co. In 1889, Clinch joined with the Chicago industrialist and noted benefactor John Crerar to form Crerar, Clinch and Co., which became a major Midwestern distributor of industrial coal and coke. By 1906, Clinch maintained control of many Hannah and Lay enterprises in Traverse City and held directorships at many of Chicago's leading railroad corporations, financial institutions, and its Auditorium Building and Hotel.
The Traverse City Refrigerator Company's business papers were maintained in the office files of its president, Milton S. Sanders, who also served as an officer of the Hannah and Lay Mercantile Co. of Traverse City.
The Traverse City Refrigerator Company's records are divided into two series: General Office Files and Minutes and Reports. The collection documents the company's administrative and business activities from 1909 to 1919.
Subjects:
Traverse City Refrigerator Company; Traverse City (Mich.); Refrigerator industry--Michigan--Traverse City.
Genre/Form:
Business records
- General Office Files
  The General Office Files (2.7 linear feet) include a range of materials that document the company's policies, products, and incorporation and dissolution, and correspondence. Of particular significance is Forrest V. Detwiler's correspondence with the parent office. Beginning with very early discussions about "the refrigerator proposition," these materials trace the company's life through the eyes of its primary salesman and expert technician. Also of interest is Floyd R. Clinch's correspondence, which offers the entrepreneur's perspective on the same developments and time period.
  - Blue Prints, Refrigerator, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Alaska Refrigerator Co., 1908-1910 (Box 1)
    - Avery, C.M., Sales Consultant, 1909-1911 (Box 1)
    - Brown and Hopkins, Attorneys for Patents and Trademark, 1909-1919, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Clinch, R. Floyd, Vice-President, 1909-1915, 14 folders (Box 1)
    - Colyer, W.H., 2nd Plant Superintendent, 1910-1911 (Box 1)
      (includes photograph)
    - Detwiler, Forrest V., Inventor and Salesman
      - January 1909-June 1912, 12 folders (Box 1)
        (includes one folder regarding Wonder Cooker and Baker)
      - July 1912-1915, 22 folders (Box 2)
    - Eaton, S.B., Stockholder, 1909-1912 (Box 2)
    - Keefe, J.S., Stockholder, 1910-1912 (Box 2)
    - Smalley, J.B., Plant Manager, 1911-1914 (Box 2)
    - Thompson, R.S., Stockholder, 1909-1914 (Box 2)
    - Ullin, C.O., McCray Refrigerator Co., 1909 (Box 2)
    - Vath, F.A., Chicago Office
      - 1911-February 1913, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - March 1913-1915, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Customer Mailing List, 1912, undated (Box 3)
  - "Desk Book," Policies and Agent Agreements, 1917-1918 (Box 3)
  - Dissolution
    - Stockholders Resolution, 1919 (Box 3)
    - Trusteeship, 1918-1919 (Box 3)
  - Federal Tax Filing, 1910 (Box 3)
  - Household Shows
    - Chicago, 1912 (Box 3)
    - Milwaukee and Ohio, 1912 (Box 3)
  - Incorporation, 1909 (Box 3)
  - Patent Details, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Product Description
    - Advertisements and Articles (Box 3)
    - Brochures (Box 3)
    - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Instructions (Box 3)
  - Prospectus, 1910-1911 (Box 3)
  - Shopfloor
    - Accident Reports and Workers Compensation Claims, 1909-1914, 1918, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Bulletins, 1911-1913 (Box 3)
    - Job Announcements, 1909-1912 (Box 3)
  - Testimonials from Customers, 1909-1913 (Box 3)
- Minutes and Reports
  The Minutes and Reports series (.3 linear feet) includes a volume of handwritten minutes from all the Stockholders and Directors Meetings -- both annual and "special" -- during the life of the company. The ledger also tracks the investors' stockholdings. Copies of the Agendas distributed at the meetings complement the minutes, though these are scattered. The Annual Reports summarize the company's sales and debts, with the May 1917 report covering 19 months of activity.
  - Annual and Special Meetings
    (Directors and Stockholders)
    - Agendas, 1909-1917 (Box 3)
    - Minutes and Stockholdings, 1909-1919 (Box 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1909, 1911-1918, 2 folders (Box 3)